Andre De Coppet Collection, 1566-1936 (bulk 1770-1865 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Andre De Coppet Collection
1566-1942
1770-1865
C0063
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
23 linear feet 35 archival boxes, 9 half-size archival boxes, 1 3.5" x 9.5" x 12.25" box, 2 22" x 28" oversize boxes, 1 16" x 20" oversize box 15 volumes
De Coppet, Andre, 1892-1953.
The Andre De Coppet Collection represents the American history-related collecting activities of American broker and collector Andre De Coppet (Princeton Class of 1915). There are numerous manuscripts, personal letters, documents, and printed material from three main periods: the Revolutionary War, the Federal Period, and the Civil War.
Andre De Coppet (1892-1953) was an American broker and collector of Americana. He was born in New York in 1892 to Edward J. and Pauline De Coppet. A 1915 graduate of Princeton University, he inherited a position in the family stock exchange firm of De Coppet & Doremus after the death of his father in 1916. In 1920 he wed Clara Barclay Onativia in New York. In the mid-1920s he took an interest in Haiti and invested in a sisal plantation there. Through the 1920s and 1930s, De Coppet amassed a significant collection of European and American manuscripts, which were bequeathed to universities upon his death in 1953.
This collection represents the American history-related collecting activities of Andre De Coppet (Princeton Class of 1915), one of the foremost American collectors of his generation. Ranging in period from the Spanish colonization of Florida (1566) to President Franklin Delano Roosevelt's first term, the collection is comprised of letters, documents, manuscripts, and printed materials from hundreds of important American historical figures. Though it spans centuries, the collection has three major foci in American history: the Revolutionary War, the Federal Period, and the Civil War. Most prominently represented are the presidents of the United States, including all from Washington through Truman. The amount of material affiliated with each individual or subject varies widely, though there are a number significant larger groups:
A group of letters and documents written by George Washington (1732-1799) spans his entire adult life and includes over 150 items. The earliest items are Virginia land surveys conducted in the 1750s. The bulk of the material dates from the years of the Revolutionary War (1775-1783). Many of the letters detail the countless important decisions Washington was forced to make as commander of America's revolutionary forces, from issues of staffing and rank to how to adequately provision soldiers with clothing and food. Also included are letters and documents from Washington's time as president, including two and a half pages of an undelivered inaugural address, and letters debating the extent of constitutional and congressional powers.
The collection includes an equally rich group of personal and professional correspondence from Washington’s trusted general Nathanael Greene (1742-1786). The Greene correspondence, dating from 1775-1785, is primarily focused on his service in the Revolutionary War, from the difficulties he experienced as quartermaster general to his appointment as commander of the Southern Army. His letters to Washington and other army officers communicate troop locations and various successes and failures of the war. In addition, they highlight the difficult conditions experienced by many Continental soldiers who lacked appropriate shoes, clothing, and food. Personal correspondence between Nathanael and his wife, brothers, and cousin reveal the family's investment in multiple privateering ventures, as well as the family ironworks, which was occasionally commissioned to make weapons for the war.
Additional materials related to the Revolutionary War abound. Correspondence and documents from dozens of American officers are filed under their respective names. A United States Continental Army file includes official muster rolls, payrolls, warrants, and ration receipts from various New England companies. A general American Revolutionary War file includes correspondence from unknown or lesser known individuals who were involved in the war or lived during the time period, as well as two lengthy manuscripts written by unidentified Englishmen, one in favor of the revolution and the other opposed.
The Asa Waterman correspondence chronicles the failures of the early commissariat system, which was established during (and in response to) the Revolutionary War. Waterman (1743-1789), originally a ship merchant, served as assistant commissary in Rhode Island from 1777 to 1780. Comprised of approximately 100 items, his correspondence highlights the difficulty of provisioning the troops with adequate, nutritious food due to a scarcity of staples (most often flour) and the problem of shipping goods at the risk of enemy seizure. His letters also address the frequent reorganization of the commissariat system and its negative effect on both the commissary officers and the troops they served.
In addition to papers of various official military officers, the collection includes the business papers of Samuel White and John Cushing, merchants and privateers during the American Revolutionary War. Privateers were sanctioned by the government to aid in the war effort by capturing enemy ships, known as "prizes." Privateers played a significant role in the war, outnumbering government-owned vessels by more than ten to one and capturing nearly 600 British ships over the course of the war. Cushing & White invested in multiple vessels that sailed along the North American coast and to the West Indies throughout the course of the war.
The collection also contains significant holdings from the post-war Federal period. Correspondence from John Adams (1735-1826) is largely focused on his role as diplomat for the newly formed American nation in the years before he became second president of the United States. His letters include strong viewpoints on the American government and his role within it. He laments the "insignificance" of his position as vice president (under George Washington), discusses the growth of democracy in various states, and complains that the American people have little tolerance for hardship.
Third U.S. President Thomas Jefferson has over 100 items in the collection. His correspondents are a veritable who's who of early American leaders. Topics range from subjects of personal interest (e.g., what materials should be used to decorate Monticello, his Virginia estate) to American agriculture, foreign diplomacy, and relations with Native Americans. Not one to mince words, Jefferson strongly states his opinions on political rivalries, government policies, and international relations, often touching on multiple issues within single letters. The letters also provide a glimpse of his scientific and inventive pursuits including a diagram for an improved water wheel and his establishment of a nail manufactory.
The collection also contains significant holdings from the American Civil War. Correspondence from Union general (and eighteenth U.S. President) Ulysses S. Grant Grant dates from 1858-1884. Many of the letters were sent directly from the battlefields of the Civil War. His correspondence with other generals and army officers captures the fevered pace and constant strategizing of the war. The progression of certain battles can be traced through the many notes he sent throughout the same day, week, or month. Telegraph notes marked "cipher" highlight the threat of enemy interception. Many of his letters in this collection were written from City Point, Virginia, the Union headquarters and base of supplies during 1864 and 1865.
Additional Civil War materials include select letters and documents from other prominent Civil War officers including Union general William T. Sherman and Confederate general Robert E. Lee, as well as a large group of official papers from the United States Army of the Potomac consisting of orders, regulations, appointments, and official correspondence. A general American Civil War file contains items relating to relatively unknown men who served in the war and wrote about their experiences; collectively, they provide a glimpse of the impact of the war on average soldiers and their families. The Frederic A. Waterhouse correspondence, between a young Union soldier and his family in Pennsylvania, vividly traces one family’s experience of the war and follows Frederic through battles, injury, and eventually death in the field.
The papers of sixteenth President Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865) form one of the largest groups in the collection. The earliest items date from Lincoln’s time as a lawyer. Included are legal briefs from all three of his formal law partnerships as well as cases from his time on the Illinois judicial circuit. Correspondence includes letters both to and from Lincoln; a handful of letters deal specifically with the Civil War. Documents from his time as president mainly consist of memoranda, discharges, pardons, commissions, and orders.
Other well-represented American presidents include Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919), whose letters reflect many of the positions he held before being elected president, and Woodrow Wilson (1856-1924), whose correspondence demonstrates his lifelong passion for the study of government and history.
Hundreds of other American individuals and subjects are covered by the collection. There are significant letters from Americans of the stature of Samuel Adams, John C. Calhoun, Henry Clay, Benjamin Franklin, and Patrick Henry, and informative and characteristic ones of such diverse personages as John Wilkes Booth, Robert Fulton, and Thomas Paine. A large group of papers from eighteenth and nineteenth-century Massachusetts is filed by town and contains many legal documents in the form of land deeds, writs, and tax forms.
Researchers should note that Andre De Coppet saved many clippings from the auctions and dealers where he purchased the items in this collection. These clippings and provenance files are available in Boxes 43 and 44.
The collection is arranged alphabetically by name of originator and/or subject; in the Miscellaneous and Provenance Files boxes (Boxes 43-44) the material is arranged alphabetically under the subject (ex.: "Washington, George.").
Researchers are required to use surrogates.
Gift of Andre Coppet, Howard Froelick, Col. Richard Gimbel.
Grant, Ulysses S., 1852-1929.; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; United States. Army of the Potomac.; United States. Continental Army.; United States. Continental Army. Commissary General's Dept.; American Loyalists -- Claims.; Presidents -- United States -- Correspondence.; Privateering -- United States -- 18th century.; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- United States -- 19th century.; Massachusetts -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 -- Sources.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain -- 18th century -- Sources.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain -- 19th century -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns and battles -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Naval operations -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Confederation, 1783-1789 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Constitutional period, 1789-1809 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Sources.; United States -- History, Military -- Sources.; United States -- History, Naval -- Sources.; Correspondence -- 18th century.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Deeds -- Massachusetts.; Diplomatic documents -- United States.; Legal documents.; Ship's papers.; Surveys (land) -- Virginia -- 18th century.; Treaties.; American history/Civil War and Reconstruction; American history/Colonial; American history/Gilded Age, Populism, Progressivism; American history/Revolution; American politics and government
- Adams, Henry Brooks (1838-1918), 1904 January 7; 1 item (Folder 1)
  Historian of American history and great grandson of John Adams. ALS on the place of literature in the past, present, and future. 4 pp.
- Adams, John (1735-1826), 1775-1816; 2 boxes (1 partial)
  John Adams served as an elected member of the First and Second Continental Congresses, a U.S. diplomat, vice president under George Washington, and second president of the United States (1797-1801). This series primarily consists of select letters written by Adams from 1775 to 1816. Recipients include prominent Americans such as John Jay (1745-1829), James Madison (1749-1812), Benjamin Rush (1746-1813), and John Trumbull (1750-1831)—who received over a third of the letters in this collection. Subject matter is nearly always political in nature whether official government communication or personal correspondence. Also included are three miscellaneous documents signed by Adams. The series is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent with the three miscellaneous documents housed in Box 46 (oversize). Many of the letters have been published in multi-volume series devoted to Adams. Two such sources were consulted in the preparation of this finding aid:
  HUP - Papers of John Adams, The Adams Papers Series (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1977-2006).
  BLP - The Works of John Adams, Select Bibliographies Reprint Series (1850-56; Reprinted Freeport, NY: Books for Libraries Press, 1969).
  Letters in this collection that are published in either of these series contain a bracketed notation in the item description including the above designated abbreviations (by publisher), volume, and page number. Since Adams often wrote multiple copies of his letters as well as kept a letter-book, multiple institutions may own copies of the same letter. An asterisk (*) in the item description designates the citing of this specific copy of the letter. RC indicates the item is the original recipient’s copy.
  - Correspondence, 1775 November 5-1816 May 22; 42 folders
    - Adams, Thomas Boylston, 1794 December 3; 1 item (Folder 1)
      ALS, Philadelphia. To son Thomas [in the Netherlands]. Updating on friends from home and encouraging intellectual and moral pursuits. 3 pp.
    - Boylston, John, 1783 June 12; 1 item (Folder 2)
      ALS (RC), Paris. Thanking Boylston for an introduction to Eliphalet Fitch and party. 1 p.
    - Carey, Matthew, 1813 June 1; 1 item (Folder 3)
      ALS, Quincy. Commending the naval exploits of Commodore Samuel Tucker during the Revolution and War of 1812 with the suggestion that Carey include Tucker in his Naval History. 2 pp.
    - Collector and Naval Officer at New York, 1800 November 14; 1 item (Folder 4)
      ALS, Washington. Recommending a Colonel Smith and requesting the recipients provide him support and assistance. 1 p.
    - Cranch, William, 1815 March 3; 1 item (Folder 5)
      ALS (RC), Quincy. On the fishery rights of the United States versus Great Britain, asking that the judge prove the treaty of 1783 is still in effect. 3 pp. [BLP: Vol. X, 131-133]
    - Gravier, Charles, 1781 July 19; 1 item (Folder 6)
      LS, Paris. To the Comte de Vergennes emphasizing the need to recognize the sovereignty of the United States and thereby allow a U.S. Minister to attend the Congress at Vienna. 6 pp. [HUP: Vol. 11, 425-430]
    - Humphreys, David, 1786 February 8-March 4; 2 folders
      - Humphreys, David, 1786 February 8; 1 item (Folder 7)
        ALS, Grosvenor Square (London). Paying tribute to Humphreys' performance of his duties as representative of the U.S. and encouraging him to reconsider his resignation. 3 pp.
      - Humphreys, David, 1786 March 4; 1 item (Folder 8)
        ALS (RC), London. Addressed to "Humphries" care of [Thomas] Jefferson, asking him to procure passage for a couple and their servant on the packet from L'Orient to New York. 1 p.
    - Jay, John, 1782 August 10-13; 2 folders
      - Jay, John, 1782 August 10; 1 item (Folder 9)
        LS, The Hague. Concerning European politics and the impossibility of meeting in Paris unless the British representative will treat with America as an independent nation. 3 pp. [HUP: Vol. 13, 227-228]
      - Jay, John, 1782 August 13; 1 item (Folder 10)
        LS, The Hague. Emphatically insisting upon patience and firmness in peace negotiations with England. 3 pp. [HUP: Vol. 13, 236-239]
    - Lincoln, General Benjamin, 1796 November 7; 1 item (Folder 11)
      ALS, Quincy. Promising to send a sum of money. 1 p.
    - Livingston, [Robert R.], 1782 August 18; 1 item (Folder 12)
      Letter (copy), The Hague. Transcribing British diplomat [Alleyne] FitzHerbert's commission from the King (in Latin) and discussing the negotiation of treaties of commerce with various European nations. Page 2 contains ANS in which Adams explains that the bracketed paragraph was not copied from his letter book or sent to Congress because he deemed it "unprudent." (See HUP for more on this.) 7 pp. [HUP: Vol. 13, 243-250]
    - Madison, James, 1812 January 17; 1 item (Folder 13)
      ALS, Quincy. Describing and recommending to the President three young men from Boston and Newburyport who desire naval appointments. 2 pp.
    - Middleton, Arthur, 1779 April 24; 1 item (Folder 14)
      ALS (RC) written "On Board the Alliance, St Lazare" concerning the plans of the Commodore [referring to Alexander Gillon] and the response of the French Court. 1 p. [*HUP: Vol. 8, 39-40]
    - Nichols, [John?], 1786 February 14; 1 item (Folder 15)
      ANS, written in third person, originally enclosing a resolution of the President and Fellows of "the University of Cambridge" Massachusetts (i.e. Harvard). 1 p.
    - Rush, Benjamin, 1808 August 31-1812 July 10; 5 folders
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1808 August 31; 1 item (Folder 16)
        ALS, Quincy. Analyzing Napoleon and the war with Great Britain, responding to an allegation that he is a "weak man," and discussing American political affairs. 4 pp.
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1809 January 23; 1 item (Folder 17)
        ALS, Quincy. Advocating the formation of a large navy and the removal of the embargo, and discussing the effects of France and England on American politics. 3 pp.
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1809 April 12; 1 item (Folder 18)
        ALS (RC), Quincy. Recounting his entrance into political life from 1770 to 1783 and dividing the period into eight sections, with mention of other prominent figures of the time including Thomas Paine, John Hancock, and cousin Samuel Adams. 5 pp. [BLP: Vol. IX, 616-619]
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1811 January 18; 1 item (Folder 19)
        ALS, Quincy. Requesting Rush [Treasurer of the U.S. Mint at Philadelphia] send specimens of coins to his son, John Quincy Adams. Also discussing the influence of Napoleon and the American Revolution on the revival of Greek and Latin studies. 3 pp
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1812 July 10; 1 item (Folder 20)
        ALS (RC), Quincy. Discussing various political issues and prominent American figures. 3 pp.
    - Rush, Richard, 1814 December 11-1815 June 11; 2 folders
      - Rush, Richard, 1814 December 11; 1 item (Folder 21)
        ALS (RC), Quincy. Introducing Francis C. Gray, discussing his reading, and commenting on the pursuit of happiness. 1 p.
      - Rush, Richard, 1815 June 11; 1 item (Folder 22)
        ALS (initials) (RC), Quincy. Discussing religion and government, mentioning prominent Europeans of the eighteenth century. 2 pp.
    - Story, Joseph, 1816 May 22; 1 item (Folder 23)
      ALS, Quincy. Eulogizing [Samuel] Dexter, who served under him as secretary of war and of the Treasury. 1 p.
    - Trumbull, John, 1775 November 5-1805 August 5; 16 folders
      - Trumbull, John, 1775 November 5; 1 item (Folder 24)
        AL (RC) signed "your Friend." Thanking him for a copy of poem McFingal, lamenting the loss of [Silas] Deane and others' services [to the Continental Congress], and expressing enthusiasm and hope towards the end of tyranny. 2 pp. [*HUP: Vol. 3, 278-279]
      - Trumbull, John, 1791 January 23; 1 item (Folder 25)
        AL with signature removed, Philadelphia. Discusses his book-- A Defence [sic] of the American Constitutions--, the condition of the government (commending Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton), and the "insignificance" of the office he holds [Vice President]. 3 pp. [BLP: Vol. IX, 572-573]
      - Trumbull, John, 1791 March 31; 1 item (Folder 26)
        ALS, Philadelphia. Concerning Alexander Hamilton's success as Secretary of Treasury, the French Revolution, different types of government, and his own conduct and response to detractors. 4 pp. Housed with separate address sheet (1 folded leaf).
      - Trumbull, John, 1793 January 31; 1 item (Folder 27)
        AL (RC) signed "your sincere friend," Philadelphia. An enigmatic letter comparing a set of men (under pseudonyms) to Mother Carey's chickens. 2 pp. Separate address sheet (1 leaf).
      - Trumbull, John, 1793 March 10; 1 item (Folder 28)
        AN (RC), Hartford. Written in third person, asking Trumbull to spend the evening at "Mr. David Bulls." 1 p.
      - Trumbull, John, 1793 March 11; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS, Hartford. Asking Trumbull for two favors: to deliver a bank bill and to procure a subscription to the Hartford paper for the "Vice President" (i.e. Adams) 2 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1793 March 18; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS, Quincy. Introducing his son, John Quincy Adams, with mention of his literary abilities and the belief that he will enter politics; referring also to [Alexander] Hamilton. 3 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1793 December 31; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS, Philadelphia. Inviting Trumbull to visit the following summer and speaking of the domestic and foreign situations. 3 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1795 January 24; 1 item (Folder 32)
        ALS, Philadelphia. Discussing the peace treaty and praising [John] Jay. Originally enclosed with copies of letters relating to the treaty, including one unsent passage which Adams emphasized be kept secret. 2 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1796; 1 item (Folder 33)
        ANS, (RC) [Hartford]. Written in third person, asking Trumbull to spend an hour with him at David Bull's house. 1 p.
      - Trumbull, John, 1797 January 19; 1 item (Folder 34)
        ALS, Philadelphia. Commending Trumbull on his improved health and a forthcoming edition of his writings. Asking his opinion on the politics of France & Spain, and the nature of humility and honor. 2 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1800 August 12; 1 item (Folder 35)
        ALS, Quincy. Regarding an interview with an unnamed citizen of New Haven who reported uneasiness in Connecticut at the removal of Secretary of State (Timothy Pickering) and who advised Adams on the condition of roads. 2 pp. [BLP: Vol. IX, 74-75]
      - Trumbull, John, 1800 September 10; 1 item (Folder 36)
        ALS, Quincy. Expressing extreme frustration with the Federalist party. 2 pp. [BLP: Vol. IX, 83-84]
      - Trumbull, John, 1805 July 8; 1 item (Folder 37)
        ALS, Quincy. Touching on a variety of topics including suspicion of foul play in the post office, the Federalist party, Connecticut politics, and a history of Mount Wollaston, his family home. 4 pp.
      - Trumbull, John, 1805 August 5; 1 item (Folder 38)